A Finding Aid to the William Penhallow Henderson Papers, 1876-1987, bulk 1876-1943, in the Archives of American Art AAA.hendwill
Archives of American Art
William Penhallow Henderson papers
bulk 1876-1943
1876-1987
AAA.hendwill
Archives of American Art
10.5 Linear feet
The papers of Chicago and Santa Fe painter, muralist, architect, and furniture designer William Penhallow Henderson measure 10.5 linear feet and date from 1876 to 1987 (bulk dates 1876 to 1943). Found within the papers are scattered biographical material; correspondence with friends and colleagues; three diaries; personal business records; two files concerning the Santa Fe Painters and Sculptors and the Art in Embassies Program; architecture, furniture, and other design project files; exhibition files; notes and writings; artwork, including 64 sketchbooks by Henderson and others; miscellaneous printed material; and photographs of Henderson, his family and colleagues.
Henderson, William Penhallow, 1877-1943
Biographical Note
Painter, architect, and furniture designer, William Penhallow Henderson was born in 1877 in Medford, Massachusetts. His father, William Oliver Henderson was a friend of painter William Edward Norton and an amateur painter himself. During Henderson's childhood, the family moved several times, settling in Turkey Creek, Texas, in 1879, and Clifton, Kansas, in 1886.
Returning to Boston in 1891, Henderson studied at the Massachusetts Normal Art School and, and in 1899, entered the School of the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, studying under Edmund C. Tarbell. In the following year, he won the Paige Traveling Scholarship for two years of study in Europe. His travels, from 1902-1903, included London, where he became acquainted with the family of John Singer Sargent. He also traveled to Paris, Berlin, Dresden, Madrid, and the Azores.
From 1904 to 1910, Henderson taught at the Academy of Fine Arts in Chicago. In 1904 he painted in Mexico and Arizona with colleague Carl N. Werntz. He married the poet-editor of Poetry magazine, Alice Corbin in 1905, and their only child, Alice Oliver Henderson, was born in 1907.
Between 1906 and 1907 Henderson completed ten murals for the Joliet Township High School. Mrs. Henderson's book Anderson's Best Fairy Tales, illustrated by her husband, provided the funds for a second trip to Europe from 1910-1911. In 1914, Henderson built a house and studio of his own design at Lake Bluff, Illinois, and in the same year he was commissioned by Frank Lloyd Wright to design murals for Midway Gardens, Chicago. Unfortunately, the murals were painted over shortly after completion. In the following year, he designed the scenery and costumes for the Chicago Fine Arts Theatre production of Alice in Wonderland.
Due to his wife's failing health, the family moved to Santa Fe, New Mexico in 1916, and in 1918, Henderson was employed by the U. S. Shipping Board Emergency Fleet Corporation in San Francisco to paint camouflage onto the hulls of ships during World War I.
In 1925, Henderson, with his first son-in-law John Evans, formed the Pueblo-Spanish Building Company, through which he designed and built many private homes and some public buildings, including the Railroad Ticket Office in Santa Fe. Henderson was also successful at designing carved wooden furniture. In the mid-1930s, he was appointed to the Federal Arts Project, for which he completed easel paintings and six murals for the Santa Fe Federal Court Building.
In 1937, Henderson completed the impressive Navajo House of Religion, built in the style of an American Indian hogan and later re-named the Museum of Navajo Ceremonial Art.
William Penhallow Henderson died in 1943 in Tesuque, New Mexico.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Chicago and Santa Fe painter, architect, and furniture designer William Penhallow Henderson measure 10.5 linear feet and date from 1876 to 1987 (bulk dates 1876-1943). Found within the collection are biographical material; a file concerning Henderson's father William Oliver Henderson; correspondence primarily with colleagues discussing art-related topics; two diaries describing his student days in Paris, 1902-1903, and one concerning the latter part of his life; personal business records; subject files for the Santa Fe Painters and Sculptors and the Art in Embassies Program; architecture and furniture files containing notes, designs, and photographs of Henderson's work in these areas; additional project files concerning other projects, including a play, architectural projects, and a mural; exhibition files; notes and writings; artwork, including 64 sketchbooks by Henderson; miscellaneous printed material; and photographs of Henderson, his family, colleagues, and artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 13 series primarily according to type of material; materials within series are arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1897-1984 (Boxes 1, 12; 14 folders)
Series 2: File on William Oliver Henderson, 1876-1906 (Box 1; 12 folders)
Series 3: Correspondence, 1883-1987 (Boxes 1-2; 1.9 linear feet)
Series 4: Diaries, 1902-1940 (Box 3; 4 folders)
Series 5: Personal Business Records, 1887-1984 (Box 3; 40 folders)
Series 6: Subject Files, 1921-1975 (Box 3; 2 folders)
Series 7: Architecture and Furniture Files, 1926-1983 (Boxes 3-4, 12, OV 14; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 8: Project Files, 1916-1942 (Boxes 4-5, 12, OV 14; 40 folders)
Series 9: Exhibition Files, 1927-1964 (Box 5; 25 folders)
Series 10: Notes and Writings, 1901-1985 (Boxes 5-6; 1.0 linear feet)
Series 11: Artwork, 1886-1929 (Boxes 6-8, OV 14; 1.9 linear feet)
Series 12: Printed Material, 1891-1988 (Boxes 8-9; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 13: Photographs, 1887-1985 (Boxes 9-11, 13; 1.6 linear feet)
Provenance
The William Penhallow Henderson papers were donated by Carlton Colquitt, on behalf of the estate of his late wife, Alice Henderson Rossin, the daughter of William Penhallow Henderson, in 1988.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Art in Embassies Program (U.S.).; Henderson, Alice Corbin, 1881-1949; Henderson, William Oliver; Santa Fe Painters and Sculptors; Architects--New Mexico--Santa Fe; Art--Study and teaching; Furniture designers--New Mexico--Santa Fe; Painters--New Mexico--Santa Fe; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Works of art
- Biographical Material, 1897-1984; Series 1; 14 Folders Boxes 1, 12
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material primarily consists of miscellaneous membership documents, legal records, address books, and biographical accounts.
  - Address Books, 1909-1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Biographical Accounts, 1937-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mailing Lists, 1928-1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marriage Certificate, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership Certificate and Award Certificates, 1897-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Oversized certificate housed in Box 12, Folder 1.
  - Camouflage Service Records, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Architect Licenses, 1928-1935 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Will of Samuel H. Richardson, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Locks of Hair, 1911, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Oversized Membership Certificate for the American Art Society, 1897 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- File on William Oliver Henderson, 1876-1906; Series 2; 12 Folders Box 1
  This series contains letters, certificates, writings, artwork, printed material, and photographs that document the life of Henderson's father, William Oliver Henderson. Included are 28 photographs of the 1898 Omaha Exposition, and several views of early frontier towns.
  - Marriage Certificate, Membership Certificates, and Letters, 1876-1906, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Diary Page, Writings, and Artwork, 1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, 1877-1905, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Others, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1877-1890 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Photographs of Family and Friends, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Frontier Town, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Houses, undated (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Travel Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Photographs of the Omaha Exposition, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Correspondence, 1883-1987; Series 3; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence consists of letters exchanged with family, friends, and colleagues. Correspondence dated after Henderson's death is primarily from his daughter, Alice, to various institutions concerning exhibitions of her father's work. There are several letters each from artists Gustave Baumann, Joseph Birren, Ernest L. Blumenschein, Maynard Dixon, Frank P. Fairbanks, E. W. Gollings, John W. Norton, Earl Reed, Jr., Joseph Lindon Smith, Maurice Sterne, Lorado Taft, and Carl Werntz, architects John Duncan Forsyth, John Gaw Meem, and William Gray Purcell, authors Peggy Pond Church, Erna Fergusson, Esther Forbes, and Carl Sandberg, and actors Tyrone Power and Roland Young. There is also a letter containing schematic drawings of architectural plans by Henderson's son-in-law, Bill Mauldin.
  - Correspondence, 1883-October 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 26-73)
  - Correspondence, November 1918-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1-82)
- Diaries, 1902-1940; Series 4; 4 Folders Box 3
  Two illustrated diaries, 1902-1903, describe Henderson's daily activities while studying art in Europe. Henderson writes about daily activities and his art studies, including meetings with Walter Gay, frequent outings to galleries and museums with Emily Sargent, and travels with fellow art student Alden Twachtman, son of John Henry Twachtman. A third diary, 1940, describes daily activities in Santa Fe.
  - Diaries (2 volumes), 1902-1903 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Loose Drawings, Receipts, Photographs, and Printed Material from Diary, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Loose Letters, Photographs, and Printed Material from Diary, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Diary, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Personal Business Records, 1887-1984; Series 5; 40 Folders Box 3
  Personal business records document Henderson's various personal and art business interests and contain deeds, sales records for artwork by Henderson, blankets created by Navajo Indians, and for books written by his wife Alice Corbin Henderson. Also found are lists of artwork, price lists, an inventory of photographs, and miscellaneous receipts.
  - Deeds, 1917-1940 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Consignment and Sales Records with Albert Roullier, 1912-1917 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Consignment and Sales Records with Arthur H. Hahlo & Co., 1915-1916 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Consignment and Sales Records with Canyon Road Art Gallery, 1968-1978 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Consignment and Sales Records with the Peters Corporation, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Records of Sales of Artwork, 1898-1984 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Records of Artwork Given as Gifts, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Lists of Artwork, 1910-1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 14-29)
  - Lists of Exhibitions and Artwork, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Price Lists, 1917-1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 31-39)
  - Inventory of Photographs, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Price Lists and Sales Records for Navajo Blankets, 1931-1934 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Travel Receipts, 1910-1911 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Book Order Receipts for Alice Corbin Henderson, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1887-1969 (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Subject Files, 1921-1975; Series 6; 2 Folders Box 3
  Subject files contain letters, notes, and printed material concerning the Santa Fe Painters and Sculptors, and the Art in Embassies Program.
  - Santa Fe Painters and Sculptors Letters, Notes, and Printed Material, 1921-1933 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Art in Embassies Program Notes, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Architecture and Furniture Files, 1926-1983; Series 7; 1 Linear feet Boxes 3-4, 12, OV 14
  Architecture and Furniture files contain notes, drawings, photographs, price lists, receipts, and printed material that reflect Henderson's work as an architect and document his work as a furniture designer.
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Architecture, undated (Box 3, Folder 47-49)
  - Architecture/Construction Notebook, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Designs for Carving, undated (Box 3, Folder 51-52)
  - Tracings Used in Carving, undated (Box 3, Folder 53-54)
    Oversized material housed in OV 14.
  - Miscellaneous Designs, undated (Box 3, Folder 55-61)
  - Notes and Designs of Bancos and Banquitos, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Notes and Designs of Beds and Daybeds, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Notes and Designs of Bookcases, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Oversized material housed in Box 12, Folder 1.
  - Notes and Designs of Book Shelves, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notes and Designs of Cases, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Notes and Designs of Chairs, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notes and Designs of Corbels, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Notes and Designs of Desks, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Notes and Designs of Doors, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Notes and Designs of Dressing Tables, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Notes and Designs of Fireplaces, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notes and Designs of Frames, 1929, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Notes and Designs of Gates, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Notes and Designs of Low-Boys, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Notes and Designs of Lounges and Couches, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Notes and Designs of Panels and Altars, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Notes and Designs of Radiator Grills (Wood), undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Notes and Designs of Screens and Spindles, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Notes and Designs of Signs, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Notes and Designs of Shrines, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Notes and Designs of Tables, undated (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - Notes and Designs of Trasteros, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Notes and Designs of Windows, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Notes and Designs of Wooden Light Fixtures, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Notes and Designs of Wardrobes, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Photographs of Bancos and Banquitos, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Photographs of Beds, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Photographs of Chairs, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of Chests, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of Couches, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Desks, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Doors, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Photographs of Dressers, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Fireplaces, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Photographs of Shelves, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Photographs of Tables, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Photographs of Trasteros, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Photographs of Miscellaneous Furniture, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Photographs of Residential Interiors, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Album of Photographs of Miscellaneous Furniture and Residential Interiors, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Notes: "Old Inventory", undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Notes on Photographs of Furniture, 1931-1983 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Recipes for Paint, Cement, Etc., 1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Notes on Geometry, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Notes on Color, undated (Box 4, Folder 46-48)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1929-1938, undated (Box 4, Folder 49-50)
  - Typescripts on Furniture and Gardens, undated (Box 4, Folder 51-52)
  - Price Lists for Furniture, 1931, undated (Box 4, Folder 53-54)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts for Furniture, 1932-1935, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material on Furniture, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Oversized Notes and Designs of Bookcases, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Notes and Designs of Cases, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Notes and Designs of Fireplaces, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Notes and Designs of Panels and Altars, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Tracings Used in Carving, undated (Box OV 14)
- Project Files, 1916-1942; Series 8; 40 Folders Boxes 4-5, 12, OV 14
  Project files contain a variety of material including correspondence, notes and writings, drawings, receipts, photographs, and printed material pertaining to specific projects undertaken by Henderson. The fact that these files include a play, architectural projects and a mural illustrates the wide range of Henderson's talents.
  - Play, Daughter of Heaven (Box 4)
    - Photographs of Dress Rehearsal, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 57-60)
    - Printed Material, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Diamond V Club, Polvadero, California (Box 4)
    - Photographs of Site, [1920s] (Box 4, Folder 62-63)
    - Tracing of Blueprint, 1920s (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Museum of Navajo Ceremonial Art, Santa Fe, New Mexico (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1942, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Notebook "Specifications for Sandpainting Hogan,", circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Inventory of Henderson Furniture at the Museum of Navajo Ceremonial Art, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1937, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Miscellaneous Writings, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Photographs of a Traditional Hogan, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Photographs of the Model, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Photographs of Construction, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 72-73)
      Oversized material housed in Box 12, Folder 3.
    - Photographs, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Photographs of Completed Museum Exterior, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - Photographs of Completed Museum Interior, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Photographs of Sandpaintings, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Negatives, circa 1927-circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - Brochure, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Buildings "Los Gallos" and "La Posta" (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1929-1930, undated (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
    - Drawings and Photographs of "La Posta,", undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Federal Court Building Murals, Santa Fe, New Mexico (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 14-17)
    - Notes and Writings, 1938, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Receipts, 1934-1937 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Drawings and Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Oversized Photographs of the Museum of Navajo Ceremonial Art, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Album of Photographs of Construction of the Museum of Navajo Ceremonial Art, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Tracing of Blueprint for the Diamond V Club, [1920s] (Box OV 14)
- Exhibition Files, 1927-1964; Series 9; 25 Folders Box 5
  Exhibition files contain correspondence, financial records, notes and writings, photographs, and printed material documenting exhibitions of Henderson's work. See also Printed Materials and Photographs for additional exhibition-related documentation.
  - Ferargil Galleries, New York, New York (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 21-26)
    - Price Lists, Writings, and Exhibition Catalog, 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Retrospective Exhibition, Museum of New Mexico, Santa Fe (Box 5)
    - Notes, 1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
    - Address List, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Typescripts, 1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 31-33)
    - Price Lists, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Receipts, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 35-37)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 39-40)
  - Solo Exhibition, Roswell Museum and Art Center, Roswell, New Mexico (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Notes, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Financial Records, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Exhibition Announcement and Catalogs, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Notes and Writings, 1901-1985; Series 10; 1 Linear feet Boxes 5-6, OV 14
  Notes and writings include notebooks, loose notes, and typescripts on miscellaneous art-related topics, and travel by Henderson, his wife Alice Corbin Henderson, and by others.
  - Notebook on Etching, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Notebooks of Geometric Calculations, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Notebooks by Alice Corbin Henderson, 1934-1947, undated (Box 5, Folder 48-50)
  - Notes on the Smart Shop, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Notes on the Studio and the Shop, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Notes on Pigments, undated (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Color Charts for Sand Paintings, undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Notes on Inspirational Quotations, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Notes on Père Marquette, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Travel Notes, 1910-1911 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Notes from Play Alice in Wonderland, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Notes on Mat and Frame Sizes, 1917-1971 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Notes on Reference Publications, 1919-1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 60-61)
  - Notes on the Santa Fe Country Club Murals, 1922, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Notes on Henderson's Death, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Notes on Certificates for Henderson Works, 1971-1978 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - List of Lenders to Exhibition at National Collection of Fine Arts, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1931-1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 66-71)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1931-1977, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
  - Poems by Henderson, 1905-1910, undated (Box 6, Folder 6-8)
  - Typescript for Exhibition Catalog, 1913 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Typescripts, 1914, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Writings by Others, 1901-1985, undated (Box 6)
    - Manuscript on Travels by Alice Corbin Henderson, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Manuscript "Col. Mallory" by Alice Corbin Henderson, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Typescript "Notes for Your Use in Selecting Indian Paintings" by Alice Corbin Henderson, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Typescripts from a Composition Course at the University of Chicago by Alice Corbin Henderson, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Typescript "The Development of Modern Indian painting" by Alice Corbin Henderson, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Typescript "From Another Age", undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Typescript Biography of William Penhallow Henderson by David Bell, undated (Box 6, Folder 17-19)
    - Typescript on Henderson by Carl Sandberg, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Manuscript for the Canyon Road Art Gallery Exhibition by Alice Henderson Rossin, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Typescript "Federal Support for the Visual Arts in the State of New Mexico: 1933-1943" by William H. Spurlock, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Typescript on Henderson by Carolyn Roberts, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous Typescripts, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Oversized Wall Plans for the Santa Fe Country Club Murals, undated (Box OV 14)
- Artwork, 1886-1929; Series 11; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 6-8, OV 14
  Artwork primarily consists of sketchbooks by Henderson. There are also unbound sketches by Henderson, a travel sketchbook by his wife Alice Corbin Henderson, artwork by others, and oversized Japanese prints. The albums of sketches were assembled by Henderson's daughter, Alice Henderson Rossin.
  - Sketchbooks, 1886-1903, undated (Box 6, Folder 25-41)
  - Sketchbooks, 1903-1920s (Box 7, Folder 1-22)
  - Album of Miscellaneous Sketches, undated (Box 7, Folder 23-27)
  - Album of Sketches of New Mexico, 1916, undated (Box 7, Folder 28-31)
  - Album of Sketches of New Mexico, 1916-1929 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - Studies for Murals, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Sketches, 1902-1919, undated (Box 8, Folder 6-9)
  - Artwork by Others, 1910-1911, undated (Box 8)
    - Sketchbook by Alice Corbin Henderson, 1910-1911 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Block Print Cover for Book on Frank Brangwyn, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)